#### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ wolfganggerlach (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

Research
Bioinformatics
Science

### Languages

English (Full Professional)
German (Native or Bilingual)

# Wolfgang Gerlach, PhD

Software Engineer at NetApp working on a Kubernetes management solution

Naperville, Illinois, United States

## Summary

Senior Software Engineer with a PhD in bioinformatics. Strong expertise in architecting and implementing complex Kubernetesnative backend solutions using Golang for industrial and scientific applications in areas such as data management, IoT and bioinformatics. Experience in design and management of Kubernetes-based production-level infrastructures, including architecting and implementing microservices and APIs, to developing and implementing novel algorithms and data structures to analyze biological sequence data. Microservice- and object-oriented, concurrent and distributed programming experience in Linux/Unix environments, strong focus on Golang.

## Experience

NetApp

Software Engineer

January 2022 - Present (1 year 11 months)

Naperville, Illinois, United States

Implementing core-functionality features for NetApp Astra, a Kubernetes management solution

Argonne National Laboratory 9 years 10 months

Programming, Sr. Analyst 2019 - January 2022 (3 years)

Lemont, Illinois, United States

- Technical management of server-side infrastructure for SAGE, an NSF-funded national-scale cyberinfrastructure to enable AI at the edge. Designed overall software architecture, planned and implemented microservices and API's to meet project requirements.
- Deployed and managed bare-metal Kubernetes production cluster (Kubespray, Rook Ceph, MetalLB) to support diverse software infrastructure

(MySQL, InfluxDB, Jenkins and other in-house developed software and web services)

- Developed IoT service to manage edge devices deployed in the field all over the US (Python, MySQL, SSH) (https://github.com/waggle-sensor/beekeeper)
- Developed an "app-store" for containerized AI applications for the edge which uses Jenkins for automated testing (https://github.com/sagecontinuum/sageecr/, Python)
- Developed a custom storage service on top of an S3 backend (https://github.com/sagecontinuum/sage-storage-api, Golang) and an OAuth2-compliant token introspection endpoint to enable token-based authentication and authorization for all user-facing web services.
- Planned internships and onboarding for about 20 students.

Bioinformatics Senior Software Engineer July 2016 - November 2019 (3 years 5 months) Greater Chicago Area

- Implementation of a CWL-compliant workflow engine for scientific applications. (Golang)
- Management of a 20+ machines CoreOS service cluster and a 500-nodes compute cluster for MG-RAST (http://metagenomics.anl.gov/)
- Installed and configured various software components, including distributed databases such as Cassandra and Elasticsearch (10-20 nodes)

Senior Software Engineer, Internet of Things October 2015 - July 2016 (10 months) Greater Chicago Area

• Waggle research project (http://wa8.gl): Responsible for the software stack of Waggle (Python, RabbitMQ, Cassandra), an Internet of Things (IoT) platform that enables sensor-driven environmental science and smart city research. This platform was used by Chicago's Array Of Things project.

Bioinformatics Senior Software Engineer April 2012 - September 2015 (3 years 6 months)

- Designed and installed a distributed fault-tolerant production server infrastructure based on CoreOS/Docker technology (a PXE-boot bare-metal deployment with 15 servers) for a scientific web service (MG-RAST, http://metagenomics.anl.gov/) with over 45,000 users.
- Supervised and organized transition of existing software stack (including Solr, MySQL, Apache, MongoDB, Memcached, Nginx and other) onto new CoreOS deployment.

• Designed and implemented an extension to a distributed multi-cloud scientific workflow system that automatically orchestrates Docker containers for individual tasks in workflows. (Golang).

## Education

Universität Bielefeld Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Bioinformatics and Genome

Universität Bielefeld

Research · (2007 - 2012)

Diplom, Applied Computer Science in the Natural Sciences · (2001 - 2007)